I'd like to have you look at this pencil.
أود أن تلقوا نظرة على هذا القلم
It's a thing. It's a legal thing.
انه شيء. انه شيء شرعي.
And so are books you might have or the cars you own.
وهكذا هي الكتب قد تكون لديكم أو السيارات التي تملكها.
They're all legal things.
كلها شرعية.
The great apes that you'll see behind me,
هذه القردة العظيمة التي ترونها ورائي
they too are legal things.
هي ايضا شرعية .
Now, I can do that to a legal thing.
الآن أستطيع فعل هذا مع كل شيء شرعي.
I can do whatever I want to my book or my car.
أستطيع أن أفعل كل ما أريده بكتابي أو سيارتي.
These great apes, you'll see.
هذه القردة,سوف ترون
The photographs are taken by a man named James Mollison
التقطت هذه الصور من قبل رجل يدعى "James Mollison"
who wrote a book called "James &amp; Other Apes."
كتب كتابا عنوانه "James و قردة اخرى"
And he tells in his book how every single one them,
و يبين في كتابه كيف ان كل واحد منهم
almost every one of them, is an orphan
تقريبا ,كل واحد منهم هو يتيم
who saw his mother and father die before his eyes.
و رأى والدته او والده يموت أمام عينيه
They're legal things.
إنهم اشياء شرعية
So for centuries, there's been a great legal wall
لذلك منذ قرون, كان هنالك حائط شرعي عظيم
that separates legal things from legal persons.
و هو الذي فرق الأشياء الشرعية عن الناس الشرعية.
On one hand, legal things are invisible to judges.
من جهة، فإن الأمور الشرعية غير مرئية للقضاة.
They don't count in law.
انها لا تعول في القانون.
They don't have any legal rights.
ليس لديهم اي حقوق قانونية.
They don't have the capacity for legal rights.
انهم لا يقدرون على الحقوق القانونية .
They are the slaves.
انهم عبيد.
On the other side of that legal wall are the legal persons.
من جهة الاخرى لهذا الحائط توجد الشخصيات الشرعية .
Legal persons are very visible to judges.
الشخصيات الشرعية مرئيون للقضاة.
They count in law.
و تاخذ بعين الاعتبار في القانون.
They may have many rights.
و لديها العديد من الحقوق.
They have the capacity for an infinite number of rights.
و لديها القدرة على التمتع بما لانهاية من الحقوق.
And they're the masters.
و هؤلاء الاشخاص هم السادة.
Right now, all nonhuman animals are legal things.
الى حد الان, كل الحيوانات الا انسانية هي شرعية.
All human beings are legal persons.
وجميع البشر هم اشخاص شرعيين.
But being human and being a legal person
و لكن كونك بشريا و كونك انسانا شرعيا
has never been, and is not today, synonymous with a legal person.
لم يكن أبدا وليس اليوم مرادفا لشخص شرعي.
Humans and legal persons are not synonymous.
البشر و الاشخاص الاعتباريين ليسا مترادفان.
On the one side,
على الجانب الواحد.
there have been many human beings over the centuries
كان هنالك العديد من البشر على مدى عدة قرون
who have been legal things.
و الذين كانوا اشياءا شرعية.
Slaves were legal things.
العبيد كانوا اشياء شرعية.
Women, children, were sometimes legal things.
نساء,أطفال, كانوا في بعض الاحيان اشياءا شرعية.
Indeed, a great deal of civil rights struggle over the last centuries
في الواقع, قدرا كبيرمن الحقوق المدنية من اجلها نضالنا على مدى القرون الاخيرة
has been to punch a hole through that wall and begin to feed
كان يجب عليها ان تحدث ثغرة في ذلك الحائط لتطعم
these human things through the wall and have them become legal persons.
هؤلاء البشر من خلال الحائط واصبحوا اشخاصا اعنبارين.
But alas, that hole has closed up.
ولكن للأسف, اغلقت هذه الثغرة .
Now, on the other side are legal persons,
الآن، على الجانب الآخر يوجد الأشخاص الاعتباريين،
but they've never only been limited to human beings.
لكنهم لم يكنوا مقتصرين على البشر.
There are, for example, there are many legal persons who are not even alive.
هناك، على سبيل المثال، العديد من الأشخاص الاعتباريين الذين ليسوا على قيد الحياة حتى.
In the United States,
في الولايات المتحدة،
we're aware of the fact that corporations are legal persons.
نحن ندرك حقيقة أن الشركات هي الشخصيات الاعتبارية.
In pre-independence India,
في مرحلة ما قبل استقلال الهند،
a court held that a Hindu idol was a legal person,
عقدت محكمة أن المعبود الهندوسي كان شخصا اعتباريا،
that a mosque was a legal person.
أن المسجد كان شخصا اعتباريا.
In 2000, the Indian Supreme Court
في عام 2000،المحكمة العليا الهندية
held that the holy books of the Sikh religion was a legal person,
رأت أن الكتب المقدسة من ديانة السيخ كان شخص اعتباري،
and in 2012, just recently,
وفي عام 2012، مؤخرا،
there was a treaty between the indigenous peoples of New Zealand
كان هناك معاهدة بين السكان الأصليين في نيوزيلندا
and the crown, in which it was agreed that a river was a legal person
والتاج، والذي تم الاتفاق عليه أن النهر كان شخص اعتباري
who owned its own riverbed.
الذي كان يملك مجرى النهر الخاص بها.
Now, I read Peter Singer's book in 1980,
الآن، وأنا أقرأ كتاب بيتر سينجر في عام 1980،
when I had a full head of lush, brown hair,
عندما كان لدي شعر خصب,شعر بني,
and indeed I was moved by it,
وقد تأثرت به بالفعل،
because I had become a lawyer because I wanted to speak for the voiceless,
لأنني قد اصبحت محاميا كنت أريد أن أتكلم عن من لا صوت له،
defend the defenseless,
و أن أدافع عن من لا دفاع له
and I'd never realized how voiceless and defenseless the trillions,
وأنا لم أدرك كيف ان من لا صوت لهم و لا دافع لهم هم تريليونات،
billions of nonhuman animals are.
بل مليارات من الحيوانات غير البشرية.
And I began to work as an animal protection lawyer.
و بدأت العمل بصفتي محامي عن الحيوانات.
And by 1985, I realized that I was trying to accomplish something
وبحلول عام 1985، أدركت أنني كنت أحاول انجاز شيء ما
that was literally impossible,
كان من المستحيل حرفيا,
the reason being that all of my clients,
والسبب هو أن كل موكلي،
all the animals whose interests I was trying to defend,
كل الحيوانات التي كنت أحاول الدفاع عنها ،
were legal things; they were invisible.
كانت امور قانونية؛ كانت غير مرئية.
It was not going to work, so I decided
لم اكن اذهب الى العمل ,لذلك قررت
that the only thing that was going to work was they had, at least some of them,
أن الشئ الوحيد الذي سيذهب الى العمل هو على الاقل ان بعض منهم
had to also be moved through a hole that we could open up again in that wall
يجب ان ينقل عبر فتحة بامكاننا فتحها مرة اخرى في هذا الحائط
and begin feeding the appropriate nonhuman animals through that hole
لتبدأ التغذية المناسبة للحيوانات غير البشرية من خلال هذه الفتحة
onto the other side of being legal persons.
على الجانب الآخر يوجد الأشخاص الاعتباريين.
Now, at that time, there was very little known about or spoken about
الآن، في ذلك الوقت، لم يكن هناك من يتحدثت حقا عن
truly animal rights,
حقوق الحيوان,
about the idea of having legal personhood or legal rights for a nonhuman animal,
عن فكرة وجود شخصية اعتبارية أو حقوق قانونية لحيوان غير بشري،
and I knew it was going to take a long time.
و كنت اعلم ان ذلك سيستغرق وقت طويل.
And so, in 1985, I figured that it would take about 30 years
وهكذا، في عام 1985، وأنا أحسب أنه سوف يستغرق حوالي 30 سنوات
before we'd be able to even begin a strategic litigation,
قبل أن نصبح قادرين على البدء حتى في التقاضي الاستراتيجي،
long-term campaign, in order to be able to punch another hole through that wall.
انها حملة على مدى طويل لنصبح قادرين على احداث فتحة اخرى في هذا للحائط
It turned out that I was pessimistic, that it only took 28.
ادركت انني كنت متشائم, هذا لن يستغرق سوى 28 سنة.
So what we had to do in order to begin was not only
اذا ماذا كان يجب علينا أن نفعل لنبدا؟ ليس فقط
to write law review articles and teach classes, write books,
كتابة مقالات قانونية وتدريس الصفوف، وكتابة الكتب،
but we had to then begin to get down to the nuts and bolts
بل كان يجب علينا البدء في التفاصيل الصغيرة والبدائية لندرك
of how you litigate that kind of case.
كيف يمكنك مقاضاة هذا النوع من القضايا.
So one of the first things we needed to do was figure out what a cause of action was,
لذلك من اول الاشياء التي كنا نحتاج القيام بها كانت معرفة ما كان سبب الدعوى,
a legal cause of action.
سبب قانوني للتحرك.
And a legal cause of action is a vehicle that lawyers use
و سبب قانوني للتحرك هو سيارة يستعملها المحامون
to put their arguments in front of courts.
لتقديم حججهم أمام المحاكم.
It turns out there's a very interesting case
و اتضح هنالك حالة مثيرة للاهتمام
that had occurred almost 250 years ago in London called Somerset vs. Stewart,
التي وقعت منذ ما يقرب من 250 عاما في لندن تسمى سومرست مقابل ستيوارت،
whereby a black slave had used the legal system
اين عبدا سود استعمل النضام القانوني
and had moved from a legal thing to a legal person.
و انتقل من شئ اعتباري الى شخصية اعتبارية.
I was so interested in it that I eventually wrote an entire book about it.
كنت مهتما كثيرا بها حيث كتبت كتاب كامل حول هذا الموضوع.
James Somerset was an eight-year-old boy when he was kidnapped from West Africa.
سنوات كان جيمس سومرست صبي يبلغ من العمر ثماني سنوات عندما تم اختطافه من غرب أفريقيا.
He survived the Middle Passage,
نجا من الممر الاوسط
and he was sold to a Scottish businessman named Charles Stewart in Virginia.
و بيع الى رجل اعمال سكتلندي يدعى شارلز ستيوارت في فيرجينا .
Now, 20 years later, Stewart brought James Somerset to London,
الان,بعد 20 سنة ستيوارت اخذ جاميس سومرست الى لندن ,
and after he got there, James decided he was going to escape.
و بعد الوصول الى هنالك قرر جاميس الفرار
And so one of the first things he did was to get himself baptized,
لذلك كانت اول الاشياء التي فعلها تعميد نفسه,
because he wanted to get a set of godparents,
لانه اراد ان يصبح لديه مجموعة من الاباء الروحين,
because to an 18th-century slave,
لان العبد في القرن 18,
they knew that one of the major responsibilities of godfathers
كان يعلم ان من المسؤولبات الاساسية للعراب
was to help you escape.
هي مساعدته على الفرار .
And so in the fall of 1771,
اذا في خريف عام 1771،
James Somerset had a confrontation with Charles Stewart.
واجه جاميس سومرست تشارلز ستيوارت.
We don't know exactly what happened, but then James dropped out of sight.
ان نكن نعام ما حدث فعلا, ولكن بعد ذلك اختفى جيمس بعيدا عن الأنظار.
An enraged Charles Stewart then hired slave catchers
وغضب تشارلز ستيوارت ثم استأجرصيادين للعبيد
to canvass the city of London,
لحشد مدينة لندن،
find him, bring him not back to Charles Stewart,
وللعثور عليه، وجلبه لا لتشارلز ستيوارت،
but to a ship, the Ann and Mary, that was floating in London Harbour,
بل لسفينة ان و ماري و التي كانت تطفو في ميناء لندن
and he was chained to the deck,
و كبل بالسلاسل الى سطح السفبنة,
and the ship was to set sail for Jamaica
وكانت السفينة قد أبحرت الى جامايكا
where James was to be sold in the slave markets
حيث كان جيمس سيتم بيعهه في أسواق العبيد
and be doomed to the three to five years of life that a slave had
و يحكم عليه من 3 سنوات الى 5 سنوات من حياته كعبد
harvesting sugar cane in Jamaica.
يحصد قصب السكر في جاميكا.
Well now James' godparents swung into action.
حسنا الان , اصبح اباء جاميس الروحين افعال.
They approached the most powerful judge,
و اقتربوا من اقوى قاضي ,
Lord Mansfield, who was chief judge of the court of King's Bench,
اللورد مانسفيلد، الذي كان رئيس محكمة مجلس الملك،
and they demanded that he issue a common law writ of habeus corpus
و طالبوا بالمثول امام قانون
on behalf of James Somerset.
يابة عن جيمس سومرست.
Now, the common law is the kind of law that English-speaking judges can make
الآن، القانون العام هو نوع من القوانين الذي يمكن للقضاة الناطقين باللغة الإنجليزية وضعه
when they're not cabined in by statutes or constitutions,
عندما لا يكون مقيدين بقوانين او دساتير,
and a writ of habeus corpus is called the Great Writ,
و امر محكمة المعتقلين يسمى الأوامر العظمى،
capital G, capital W,
العاصمة G، العاصمة W
and it's meant to protect any of us who are detained against our will.
والتي من المفترض أن تحمي أي واحد منا من الذين يحتجزون ضد إرادتنا.
A writ of habeus corpus is issued.
و تم اصدار امر احضار.
The detainer is required to bring the detainee in
و طلب من الحاجز احضار المعتقل الى الداخل
and give a legally sufficient reason for depriving him of his bodily liberty.
و اعطوا سببا قانونيا لحرمانه من حريته الجسدية.
Well, Lord Mansfield had to make a decision right off the bat,
حسنا,كان اللورد مانسلفيند مطالبا باتخاذ قرار منذ البداية,
because if James Somerset was a legal thing,
لانه , اذا كان جاميس سومسرت شيء شرعي
he was not eligible for a writ of habeus corpus,
فهو لم يكن مؤهلا لأمر الإحضار,
only if he could be a legal person.
الا اذا كان شخصا قانونيا .
So Lord Mansfield decided that he would assume,
لذلك قرر اللورد مانسفيلد انه يريد حمل هذا على عاتقه،
without deciding, that James Somerset was indeed a legal person,
دون تحديد ان جاميس سومرست كان في الواقع شخصا اعتباريا,
and he issued the writ of habeus corpus, and James's body was brought in
و اصدر أمر احضار , واحضر جاميس
by the captain of the ship.
من قبل قبطان السفينة.
There were a series of hearings over the next six months.
و كان هنالك سلسلة من جلسات الاستماع على مدى ستة اشهر.
On June 22, 1772, Lord Mansfield said that slavery was so odious,
في 22 جوان من سنة 1772,اقر اللورد مانسفيلد ان الرق كان فظيعا،
and he used the word "odious,"
و إستخدم كلمة ''فظيعا" في ذلك،
that the common law would not support it, and he ordered James free.
و اقر ان القانون العام لا يمكنه تحمل ذلك، فامر بعتق جاميس.
At that moment, James Somerset underwent a legal transubstantiation.
في تلك اللحظة، جيمس سومرست خضع لعملية الاستحالة القانونية.
The free man who walked out of the courtroom
الإنسان الحر الذي سار مغادراً قاعة المحكمة
looked exactly like the slave who had walked in,
بدا تماما كالعبد الذي إتى إلى نفس القاعة،
but as far as the law was concerned, they had nothing whatsoever in common.
ولكن بقدر ما يتعلق الأمر بالقانون، كان لديهم أي شيء على الإطلاق مشترك.
The next thing we did is that the Nonhuman Rights Project,
والشيء التالي الذي فعلناه هو مشروع الحقوق الغير بشرية,
which I founded, then began to look at what kind of values and principles
الذي قمت بتأسيسه , ثم شرعت في البحث في اي نوع من القيم و المبادئ
do we want to put before the judges?
نريد ان نضع أمام القضاة
What values and principles did they imbibe with their mother's milk,
ما هي القيم والمبادئ التي اكتسبها مع حليب أمهاتهم؟
were they taught in law school, do they use every day,
هل تعلموا في كلية الحقوق؟ هل يستعملون كل يوم ,
do they believe with all their hearts -- and we chose liberty and equality.
هل يؤمنون من كل قلوبهم ؟ و نحن نختار الحرية و المساواة.
Now, liberty right is the kind of right to which you're entitled
الان , حق الحرية هي نوع من الحقوق التي لك الحق فيها
because of how you're put together,
بفضل كيف وضعتومه جميعا ,
and a fundamental liberty right protects a fundamental interest.
و حق الحرية الاساسية يحمي المصالح الاساسية.
And the supreme interest in the common law
والمصلحة العليا في القانون العام
are the rights to autonomy and self-determination.
هي الحق في الحكم الذاتي وتقرير المصير.
So they are so powerful that in a common law country,
لذلك هم أكثر قوة في القانون العام للدولة ,
if you go to a hospital and you refuse life-saving medical treatment,
اذا ذهبت الى المستشفى و رفضت العلاج الطبي المنقذ للحياة ,
a judge will not order it forced upon you,
القاضي لا يمكن ان يامر بفرضه عليك,
because they will respect your self-determination and your autonomy.
لانهم سيحترمون حقك في تقرير مصيرك و سيحترمون الحكم الذاتي الخاص بك.
Now, an equality right is the kind of right to which you're entitled
الان , حق الحرية هي نوع من الحقوق التي لك الحق فيها
because you resemble someone else in a relevant way,
لانك تشبه شخصا اخر يطريقة ما ,
and there's the rub, relevant way.
و هذا هو الاحتكاك,بطريقة ما.
So if you are that, then because they have the right, you're like them,
لذلك اذا انت هكذا, ذلك لان لهم الحق, و انت مثلهم,
you're entitled to the right.
انت تتمتع بالحق.
Now, courts and legislatures draw lines all the time.
الان , المحاكم و المشرعين يرسمون الخطوط طوال الزمن.
Some are included, some are excluded.
يتم تضمين بعض و تم استبعاد بعض.
But you have to, at the bare minimum you must --
لكن يجب كحد ادنى
that line has to be a reasonable means to a legitimate end.
ان تكون لهذه الخطوط معنى مسؤول في ظل نهاية مشروعة.
The Nonhuman Rights Project argues that drawing a line
مشروع حقوق الغير البشريجادل ان رسم خط
in order to enslave an autonomous and self-determining being
بغاية استعباد ذات مستقلة ت قرر مصيرها بنفسها
like you're seeing behind me,
كما ترونه ورائي,
that that's a violation of equality.
هذا انتهاك للمساواة .
We then searched through 80 jurisdictions,
بحثنا ضمن ثمانين اختصاصيا ,
it took us seven years, to find the jurisdiction
و أخذ من ذلك 7 سنولت, لنجد الاختصاصي
where we wanted to begin filing our first suit.
اين اردنا ان نبدا برفع اول دعوى لدينا .
We chose the state of New York.
اخترنا ولاية نيويورك.
Then we decided upon who our plaintiffs are going to be.
ثم قررنا من الذي سيكون المدعي.
We decided upon chimpanzees,
فاتفقنا علر الشامبنزي,
not just because Jane Goodall was on our board of directors,
ليس لان جاميس غودل كان على مجلس ادارتنا ,
but because they, Jane and others,
ولكن لأنهم ، جان والاخرون،
have studied chimpanzees intensively for decades.
درسوا الشامبنزي بشكل مكثف على مدى عدة عقود.
We know the extraordinary cognitive capabilities that they have,
نحن نعرف القدرات المعرفية الخارقة للعادة التي لديهم,
and they also resemble the kind that human beings have.
كم ان هذه القدرات تشبه النوع الذي يمتلكه البشر.
And so we chose chimpanzees, and we began to then canvass the world
فاخترنا الشامبنزي و بدأنا ثم حشد العالم
to find the experts in chimpanzee cognition.
لنجد الخبراء في الإدراك الشمبانزي .
We found them in Japan, Sweden, Germany, Scotland, England and the United States,
وجدناهم في اليابان, السويد ,المانيا, سكوتلندا, انقاترا و الولايات المتحدة,
and amongst them, they wrote 100 pages of affidavits
و غيرها , وكتبوا 100 صفحة من الافادات
in which they set out more than 40 ways
التي نصوا عليها بأكثر من 40 طربقة
in which their complex cognitive capability,
و التي جمعت فيها قدراتهم المعرفية,
either individually or together,
سوى كانت فردية او جماعية ,
all added up to autonomy and self-determination.
كلها اضيفت الى الحق في الحكم الذاتي و تقرير المصير.
Now, these included, for example, that they were conscious.
الان, يشمل هذا, على سبيل المثال, انهم كانوا واعيين.
But they're also conscious that they're conscious.
و لكنهم كذلك واعون بانهم واعون.
They know they have a mind. They know that others have minds.
يعلمون ان لديهم عقل. يعلمون ان الاخرين لديهم عقول.
They know they're individuals, and that they can live.
يعلمون انهم افراد, و ان بامكانهم العيش.
They understand that they lived yesterday and they will live tomorrow.
يدركون انهم عاشوا البارحة و انهم سوف يعيشون غدا.
They engage in mental time travel. They remember what happened yesterday.
يخوضون في السفر عبر الزمن العقلي. يتذكرون ما حدث بالأمس .
They can anticipate tomorrow,
يمكنهم ان يتوقعوا غدا,
which is why it's so terrible to imprison a chimpanzee, especially alone.
وهذا هو السبب لماذا هو رهيب جدا سجن الشمبانزي ، وحدها على وجه الخصوص.
It's the thing that we do to our worst criminals,
هذا هو الشيء الذي نقوم به لأسوأ المجرمين لدينا،
and we do that to chimpanzees without even thinking about it.
ونحن نفعل ذلك لالشمبانزي دون حتى التفكير فيه .
They have some kind of moral capacity.
لديهم نوع ما من القدرة الاخلاقية.
When they play economic games with human beings,
عندما يلعبون العابا اقتصادية مع البشر,
they'll spontaneously make fair offers, even when they're not required to do so.
انهم يضعون تلقائيا عروضا عادلة, حتى عندما ليسوا محتاجين لذلك.
They are numerate. They understand numbers.
انهم يعرفون العد. انهم يدركون الارقام .
They can do some simple math.
يمكنهم تجسيد بعض الرياضيات البسيطة.
They can engage in language -- or to stay out of the language wars,
يمكنهم ان يخوضوا في الغة او البقاء بعيدا عن حروب الغة,
they're involved in intentional and referential communication
انهم يشاركون في التواصل المقصود والمرجعي
in which they pay attention to the attitudes of those
الذي فبه ينتبهون الى مواقف اولائك
with whom they are speaking.
الذين يتحدثون معهم.
They have culture.
لديهم ثقافة.
They have a material culture, a social culture.
لديهم ثقافة مادية , ثقافة اجتماعية.
They have a symbolic culture.
لديهم ثقافة رمزية.
Scientists in the Taï Forests in the Ivory Coast
العلماء في غابات "تاي" في سواحل العاج
found chimpanzees who were using these rocks to smash open
وجدوا ان الشمبنزي الذين كانوا يستعملون هذة الصخور لسحق
the incredibly hard hulls of nuts.
المكسرات الصلبة بشكل لا يصدق .
It takes a long time to learn how to do that,
و يأخذ هذا وقتا طويلا لتعلم كيفية فعل هذا,
and they excavated the area and they found
و حفر العلماء هذه المنطقة و وجدوا
that this material culture, this way of doing it,
ان هذه الثقافة المادية , هذه الطريقة في فعل هذا,
these rocks, had passed down for at least 4,300 years
هذه الصخور,مضى عليها ما لا يقل عن 4300 ستة
through 225 chimpanzee generations.
خلال 225 جيلا من الشامبنزي.
So now we needed to find our chimpanzee.
لذلك نحن نحتاج الان الى ايجاد الشامبنزي الذي لدينا.
Our chimpanzee,
الشامبنزي الذي لدينا.
first we found two of them in the state of New York.
في بداية الامر وجدنا اثنين منهم في نيويورك.
Both of them would die before we could even get our suits filed.
كلاهما سوف يموت قبل ان نستطيع الحصول على الدعاوي المقدمة لدينا.
Then we found Tommy.
ثم وجدنا تومي.
Tommy is a chimpanzee. You see him behind me.
تومي هو شمبنزي. انتم ترونه خلفي .
Tommy was a chimpanzee. We found him in that cage.
تومي كان شمبنزي . وجدناه في هذا القفص.
We found him in a small room that was filled with cages
وجدناه في غرفة صغيرة كانت مليئة بالاقفاص
in a larger warehouse structure on a used trailer lot in central New York.
في هيكل مستودع كبير كثير الاستعمال في وسط مدينة نيويورك.
We found Kiko, who is partially deaf.
وجنا كيكو الذي كان اصم جزئيا.
Kiko was in the back of a cement storefront in western Massachusetts.
كان كيكو خاف واجهة اسمنتية في غرب ماساتشوستس.
And we found Hercules and Leo.
و وجدنا هيرقل و ليو.
They're two young male chimpanzees
انهم ذكور شمبنزي يافعين
who are being used for biomedical, anatomical research at Stony Brook.
الذين تم استخدامهم للطب الحيوي , بحث تشريحي في ستوني بروك.
We found them.
وجدناهم.
And so on the last week of December 2013,
و في الاسبوع الاخير من شسهر ديسمبر 2013,
the Nonhuman Rights Project filed three suits all across the state of New York
رفع مشروع حقوق غير البشر ثلاث دعاوي في جميع انحاء مدينة نيويورك
using the same common law writ of habeus corpus argument
باستخدام نفس القانون العام مع قانون محكمة المعتقلين
that had been used with James Somerset,
الذي استخدم مع جاميس سومرست,
and we demanded that the judges issue these common law writs of habeus corpus.
وطالبنا أن تصدر القضاة أحكام القانون العام لمحكمة المعتقلين.
We wanted the chimpanzees out,
أردنا بها الشمبانزي،
and we wanted them brought to Save the Chimps,
ونحن نريد منهم جلبها لإنقاذ الشمبانزي،
a tremendous chimpanzee sanctuary in South Florida
للشمبانزيملجأ هائل في جنوب فلوريدا
which involves an artificial lake with 12 or 13 islands --
الذي ينطوي على بحيرة اصطناعية مع 12 أو 13 الجزر -
there are two or three acres where two dozen chimpanzees live
هناك نوعان أو ثلاثة أفدنة حيث يعيش عشرين الشمبانزي
on each of them.
على كل واحد منهم.
And these chimpanzees would then live the life of a chimpanzee,
و هذه الشمبنزي تعيش اذا حياة الشمبنزي,
with other chimpanzees in an environment that was as close to Africa as possible.
مع شمبانزي أخرين في محيط يشبه كثيرا افريقيا.
Now, all these cases are still going on.
الان,كل هذه القضايا مازالت مستمرة.
We have not yet run into our Lord Mansfield.
نحن لم نواجه بعد ربنا مانسفيلد.
We shall. We shall.
نحن سوف نفعل ذلك.
This is a long-term strategic litigation campaign. We shall.
هذه استراتيجيةحملة التقاضي طويلة الأمد. نخن سوف نفعل ذلك.
And to quote Winston Churchill,
وعلى حد تعبير ونستون تشرشل،
the way we view our cases is that they're not the end,
الطريقة التي ننظربها الى قضايانا هي ان هذه القضايا ليست النهاية.
they're not even the beginning of the end,
ليست حتى بداية النهاية,
but they are perhaps the end of the beginning.
لكن يمكت ان تكون نهاية البداية.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم .
(Applause)
(تصفيق)